Guide to the Vincent Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Vincent family papers
1850-1940
MS 523
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of addresses, manuscripts, notes, printed material and articles of John Heyl Vincent and his son, George Edgar Vincent concerning Sunday-school classes, biblical history, sociology, education and public health.
Vincent family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George E. Vincent and Gladys E. Russell, 1939-1941.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Vincent Family papers contains papers of John Heyl Vincent and his son George Edgar Vincent. The John Vincent material is largely undated, and consists for the most part of short, often fragmentary, addresses, manuscripts, and notes about Palestine, biblical history, and related topics. Many of the materials seem directed toward children. Some may have been used by Vincent in writing one or more of his books; others, for instance a series of "Conversations", appear to be skits for performance by Sunday school classes. Also included are a few pamphlets and leaflets and a number of newspaper clippings.
George Vincent's papers consist of texts and abstracts of speeches and articles on various topics in the fields of sociology, education, and public health (1912-1940). Included are a series of lectures delivered in Scandinavia under the auspices of the American-Scandinavian Foundation in 1933.
These papers were donated by George E. Vincent and by Gladys E. Russell between 1939 and 1941.
Biographical / Historical
John Heyl Vincent, bishop and author, was born in Tuscaloosa, Alabama on February 23, 1832. He began to preach in 1850 and studied at the Wesleyan Institute in Newark, New Jersey. Vincent preached throughout New Jersey and Illinois (1851-1865), and was active in the Sunday school movement. He was one of the founders, in 1874, of the Chautauqua Assembly. Vincent was a preacher at Harvard, Yale, Cornell, Wellesley, and other colleges. He retired from active episcopate in 1904 and died on May 9, 1920. George Edgar Vincent, educator, was born in Rockford, Illinois on March 21, 1864, the son of John Heyl and Elizabeth Vincent. He received his B.A. from Yale (1885) and his Ph.D. from the University of Chicago (1896). Vincent held various positions with the Chautauqua Institution (1886-1937) and taught at the University of Chicago (1892-1911). From 1911-1917 he was president of the University of Minnesota. In 1917 Vincent became president of the Rockefeller Foundation, a position he held until his retirement in 1929. He died on February 1, 1941.
Public health; Sunday school literature; Clergy; Educators; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar), 1864-1941; Vincent, John Heyl, 1832-1920; Vincent family
- Inventory
  - John Heyl Vincent
    - "Conversations", [ca. 1850-1900] (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - "Travels in Palestine" and other writings, [ca. 1850-1900] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks, [ca. 1850-1900] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes, [ca. 1850-1900] (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Addresses and programs for class activities, [ca. 1850-1900] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Printed matter: pamphlets and leaflets, [ca. 1850-1860] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Printed matter: pictures, maps and clippings, [ca. 1850-1900] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - George Edgar Vincent
    - Writings, 1888, 1912-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 14)
    - Writings, 1926-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 15 - 21)